whose hearts are troubled, all who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism
to see and to know reality as it truly
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen De Young,
post this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening to you all.
giant killers, dragon slayers, stompers of scorpions. You are listening to the Lord of Spirits
podcast and my most esteemed co-host, the very reverend doctor, Steven D'Yong, is with me from
Lafayette Louisiana in the midst of the swamp. And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick in the
beautiful forests and hills of Emmaus, Pennsylvania. And we're live. And if you are listening to us live,
Although we know that 99% of you are not, but if you are listening to us live...
you can call us at 855-237-2346 and you can talk to us.
We're gonna get to your calls in the second half of the show
and our own Montesca Trudy will be taking those calls.
We've got some competition tonight too.
I don't know if you can.
Oh yeah?
Yeah, they're having the WrestleMania 40.
Oh man.
Press conference in about an hour,
live from Las Vegas.
Oh, so you're saying we have to get this done in an hour
so you can...
No, no, that's fine.
I'm just saying.
you know, people are attention to it.
And the air to the Swanson Frozen Food Fortune
is interviewing Vladimir Putin right now as well.
I heard that.
That it's airing.
So I could have told them not to go up against Lord of Spirits,
right?
This is a band programming decision.
Try to be with us, right?
I think there's a big audience overlap there for sure.
But what can you do?
What can it be?
doggy dog world here in internet radio. Yeah, yeah. Well, that said, when speaking of Jesus as the Messiah,
most people will point to the many Old Testament prophecies of the Messiah that He fulfilled,
the acts that He did which fit with what the prophets foretold. And this is, of course,
is a good and correct thing to do. Yet such an affirmation may overlook...
a question we should ask about what is actually happening in the gospels.
What did the people who met Jesus in person mean? When they pointed at Him and identified Him as
the Messiah? How did they recognize Him to be the Messiah even when He had not yet done most or in
some cases any of the actions that we now look back on in retrospect and match up with His whole
life and ministry.
What was it about their experience of him on the ground that made them say this is the Christ?
So Father Stephen is this actually just another episode defining what the word Messiah means?
Yes, oh, but also no
Like that pirate. Yeah, that meme. I don't even know it show that's from but that's the yes, but actually no meme looks like a wall is in grommet
to me. Hmm. Yeah. Yeah
so
Yeah, we we do need to disambiguate here a little at the beginning right because we already did
We already did
a full episode on sort of the concept of the Messiah especially at Second Temple, Jewish literature the different concepts of the Messiah
Sometimes of Messiah's and that kind of thing and we are not
Retreading that here tonight at least not that much right
This is as in your intro.
We're coming at this from another angle.
But so we talked about all that.
We talked about Meshiic in Hebrew, Christos and Greek, meaning the anointed one.
This is particularly associated with an anointed king with the Davidic king.
We also talked about how there were, we find in second-tip literature with some groups,
they were expecting multiple Messiahs.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
like a Messiah who's...
the son of David who's a king, a Messiah who's sort of a priestly Messiah who is going to
restore the temple and the priesthood to its proper worship, sort of purify it.
And the king, Lee Messiah was more focused on basically getting rid of the Romans, but
It is a broader sense removing Israel or Judea from an era of foreign oppressors right to to have its own
independent kingdom again. But so all of that was sort of about, well, what was the
messianic expectation? When you said the word Messiah to a first century Jewish person,
what was in their head? Right? So that was yeah. So that was approaching it from one angle.
And what we're doing tonight is coming from a different angle.
you said. So because when the New Testament authors, and that's
including like the authors of the Gospels, but also St. Paul,
St. James, right? St. Jude, St. Peter, when they write the
documents that become the New Testament. The key claim that every
every one of those documents is making, right?
That it's based on the key idea, right,
from which everything else flows is that Jesus is the Messiah.
Yeah.
I mean, it's almost all John's Gospel ends, particularly.
You know, these are written that you may believe
that Jesus is the Messiah, that Jesus is the Christ.
Right.
And all the letters within the first several words
Jesus Christ. And...
We hear that so much.
You know, there are literally people out there who think that's like Jesus's last name. Yeah, like his parents were Joseph and Mary Christ and then he was
At one point
In the past when I was teaching a high school Sunday school class
I
Had a student ask me what I
Had a student ask me what Jesus middle name was because they had that presupposition
And so I gave the whole explanation.
right? That's that's a title that means the Messiah that's not his last name. And the
response to me was, no, no, I know it starts with an H. Yeah. So they ended up kind of
telling on their parents. But, um, yeah. Well, you know, maybe they're just maybe they're
a, you know, um, Messianics as they call them. So they're calling, you know, Hamashia.
Yeah, there we go. There we go. There you go. See? I want to think they can't
There you go.
Right.
I want to
think the best of everything. So, but so that every time you see, every time you see in an
English New Testament, Jesus Christ, you should what you should think in your head what that's
actually saying is Jesus the Messiah. Yeah. Right. And so that claim gets made early and often
in every text, right?
And so what do they mean when they say that?
Right. And somebody made me at least say, well, all those things you said to the other episode that they were expecting about the Messiah, they were just saying, that's Jesus. Right.
Yeah.
But a bunch of those things Jesus didn't do.
Yeah. And there's some at that time.
There's some he hasn't even quite done yet. Yeah. Yeah.
So Jesus didn't overthrow the Romans.
Right.
Romans were still around.
In fact, the Romans became more brutal
and destroyed Jerusalem.
Right.
He didn't go and restore the priesthood in the temple.
Right. On this earth, like the physical building.
Yeah.
Right. Didn't get rid of the sagesis.
The Romans did, but not in the way the Messiah was supposed to.
And they weren't saying
Well, okay, there's this checklist of messiatic expectations.
And well, we got the majority of these checked off from Jesus
so that he was me the Messiah.
Right?
And they very much did not think of it in terms of Jesus
fulfilling a list of prophecies in the Old Testament.
Let me expand on that for a minute.
Ah
Because yeah, this is a problem in Christian apologetics.
I know a lot of people.
Yeah, I was gonna say we should say by the way, just to head off all the people that are,
you know, throwing whatever against the wall.
We're not saying that Jesus did not fulfill those prophecies.
No, no, not saying that.
No, no.
He did.
But what I'm going to say is, right?
Um.
If a Jewish person says to you,
name one prophecy of the Old Testament
that Jesus uniquely fulfills,
you're not gonna be able to come up with one.
Let's get a satisfaction.
Right, I mean, it's not like they haven't had a chance
to read the thing.
Yeah, but you're gonna say,
well, see Jesus was born in Bethlehem.
Lots of people born in Bethlehem.
Yes.
Right.
Thank you.
That's, you know, road into Jerusalem on a donkey.
Lots of people did that too, right?
Yeah.
Like that's not how Old Testament prophecy works.
Right.
And it's not even like, well, okay yeah,
lots of people did each of those individual things,
but we're gonna ball up a whole bunch
and say, see Jesus did all these things, right?
And then the skeptical person is going to look at you and say, yeah, that's confirmation bias because he didn't overthrow the Romans, he didn't
restore the physical temple, he didn't
So that's not how prophecy works
Right, that's not how
That's not how prophecy works
Jesus does fulfill every prophecy about the Messiah, right?
But prophecy doesn't work in that sort of
specific present print.
prediction, check it off the list way. And we've talked about that before on the show.
Yes.
So nobody should be too shocked.
Major sub-theme of this entire program.
But don't take that bait is what I'm saying.
And also, it's important, sorry, preters, that they were not saying, oh, hey, that whole Messiah thing,
Jesus took care of that so don't worry about it anymore.
Right. And that's part of this incorrect view of prophecy. Like, oh, that prophecy is fulfilled. Okay, forget about it.
Okay, it's done. Right.
That's not what they menu because because they Jesus is the Messiah is what they're saying. Not he was not he was the Messiah.
Therefore this Messiah's stuff is over.
He is the Messiah.
But by saying he is the Messiah, they were also not saying he will be the Messiah.
Right, they're not just saying he will be the Messiah. What do I mean by that? Well,
we've talked on the show before in the Messiah episode and elsewhere that there is within the
Hebrew Scriptures. This idea that the Messiah would come and that the Messiah would return and that
there is some period of time in between.
Right that
For example probably the Locust Classicas for this is Psalm 110
109 in the Greek
Which as we've mentioned before on the show probably several times is the most quoted
Old Testament text in the New Testament that talks about the Messiah raining in the midst of his enemies
Right the Lord said to my Lord sit at my right hand till I make your enemies
the footstool of your feet, right? So that there is this period where the Messiah
reigns in the mid...
to his enemies. We talked about the long time in Daniel and we talked there's a bunch of places.
And the Messiah ultimately returns to judge the living of the dead, right? The day of the Lord,
the Messiah judges the living of the dead. But they weren't just saying, Jesus is going to be the
Messiah when he comes back. They weren't just saying, oh yeah, he didn't do some of that stuff. The
The first time he was here, he's gonna do that stuff later
when he comes back.
right? That's not what they're saying. They're saying he is the Messiah. And they started
saying this about him pretty early on as disciples, right? St. Peter in particular, before
he had died before he had risen, right?
Before they even understood, right?
Say Peter...
identifies Jesus as the Messiah and then argues with him about whether he's going to die or not.
Right? So clearly that element, he still doesn't understand, but he's still identifying Jesus as the Messiah
for some reason. And so the New Testament texts, whether we're talking about the Gospels that are
narrating Jesus' life in ministry and then portraying him as the Messiah.
or we're talking about in the epistles
that are speaking from a different vantage point,
describing, but describing who Jesus is,
what He does, what He has done, what He will do.
Right?
They are also framing Him as the Messiah.
Messiah is His identity.
Yeah.
Is the claim that's being made.
And so without having done the
those things, they still make this identification. So what is it? What is it that they saw
that caused them to make this this conclusion? Yes, and that's what our that's what our
episode is about tonight. Yes, yes. So this may be a new record where we're this far
an episode and we haven't even started the episode.
already revealed what it's really all about.
Yes, we're just disambiguating the topic.
Right, so that's what we're going to be talking about.
And we're going to be talking about three main things that they identify about Jesus.
And conveniently, this show has three halves.
Because as Aristotle told us, everything that comes in three is perfect.
That's where we're going.
That's where we're going tonight.
And so for the rest of this first half, we're going to be talking about the first one of these things.
And that is that they came to see Jesus as the Messiah, because they saw that Jesus embodied Israel, the people of Israel.
Yeah. The experience, the historical experience of Israel was embodied and embodied.
Jesus as a person. Yeah, you know, hear this talked about very much. Jesus as living out the story of Israel
in himself. Yeah. Yeah, but this is especially for example, St. Matthew's gospel, you're not going to
get it all if you don't get this. Yeah, sure. And you're not going to understand what he's doing with
with Old Testament quotes. I mean, right off the bat, right? You get things in St. Matthew's gospel
Like, Herod starts to murder all of...
the children under two years old from in and around Bethlehem.
Right?
So, the saints Joseph, say Joseph in the Theotokos,
flee with Christ to Egypt.
And then after they hear Herod dies, they come back.
And St. Matthew says, as it is written,
right, out of Egypt I have called my son.
Right.
And if you're a modern person, right, you look at that and go, hold on a second,
and you flip back into the Old Testament.
Yeah, this is the 11.
Yeah.
And you say, wait, this is talking about Israel.
This is talking about God bringing Israel out of Egypt like in the Exodus.
This is the time about Jesus going to Egypt.
for a little while, then coming back, right? And then if you're a conservative modern person,
you say, no, Hosea was talking about Jesus going to Egypt and coming back. It's not about Israel, right?
Yeah, but I have to do is read the second verse in that chapter to know that it's, it definitely
is about Israel. Right? Like it says, you know, when Israel was a child, I loved him and out of Egypt,
I called my son and then...
the more they were called, the more they went away, they kept sacrificing to the bails and
burning offerings to idols. That's not Jesus. Yeah. He's not his brother or his brother. Exactly.
Right. Yeah. So this is very clear. Right. So this is not Saint Matthew just being goofy at taking
things radically out of context. Right. Right. He's trying to communicate. Jesus in his life
is embodying recapit-
insulating, uh, uh,
experiencing the experience of Israel, right? Because why did Israel go into Egypt?
Israel was brought into Egypt through Joseph to save
the family from a famine.
Yeah, right. And then once that danger was well over, God brought Israel out of Egypt. So in the same way,
Jesus, it is in
as Israel was in their infancy, is protected by going into Egypt, but then is brought back out of Egypt.
This is what's going on with Christ's temptation in the desert.
He goes out into the desert for 40 days and 40 nights.
And this is and there he's tempted or
tested right and those verbs that are used of Jesus a lot of people go down the psychological weird trails with this like
No Jesus was actually tempted right like you thought about doing bad things like no
There are there are whole weird heretical theologies for the 19th century based on trying to put that out
Yes
Yeah, this is these are the same verbs that are used
the same verbs that are used.
to describe what happens with Israel for the 40 years in the desert.
The 40 years in the wilderness, there they were tested.
And if you've read your Torah, your Pentateuch,
then you know that Israel failed and that whole generation died in the desert.
Whereas
Jesus has the parallel experience
but succeeds. Right? But succeeds. He is tested
gives glory to God, does not worship other gods, right?
Is dependent on God for food and water like the mana and the water. Remember Israel grumbled and said they were brought out there to die
in all this right so that the the temptations quote-unquote that Jesus
deals with from the devil are not
random
um
They are all the things that Israel fell into, right?
in that same experience, right? But so Jesus re-embodies that but successfully, but faithfully to God.
We just, not that long ago, had a Theophany episode, right? And we talked about in the himnography and in the Old Testament readings
how Christ passing through the Jordan was connected to Joshua leading the people through.
the Jordan which parted in front of them, right, as they came into the land in order to
conquer it. So, right, shares that experience as he comes back into the land. We've talked
about, I guess we have to mention giants once per episode. Some people think it's all we
ever talk about. So, if we don't mention it at least once per episode, like those people
would be proven wrong and we can't have that.
Yeah, we don't want them to be wrong.
I mean, what next?
Do you do an episode where we don't mention giants?
Next, we're gonna start quoting church fathers
or something.
We're not always mentioning Enoch.
Yeah.
You blew it.
You just did, anyway.
Oh, dang it.
So.
So this many days since Enoch was mentioned
on the Lord of Spirits pocket.
But we've mentioned before how the view at least of,
of right regardless of what you want to think.
Think what you will, but the view of the common Jewish people of the first century was
what was that the unclean spirits, the demons that are possessing people who Christ was
casting out of people, that those were the spirits of the dead giants, meaning they
were the same enemies.
Yeah, that was that was the belief at the time.
Yes.
Again, you can think whatever you want about that belief.
We're not saying that this is what the scripture says, or this is what the church teaches.
just
Right.
And so the prominence in the first three gospels of exorcisms is part of this.
Again, portraying Christ's experience as parallel with that of Israel.
But again, Israel, when they went into the land, did not take all the land they were
supposed to take.
Right.
They did not fight off all the giants.
They did not get rid of the giant clans as they were supposed to.
They didn't do what they were supposed to, but Christ does.
use a success.
does these things. And then even in St. Matthew's gospel another example, the way he frames the
sermon on the mount and why it's called that, right? He goes up on a mountain, which wouldn't
have been a mountain. It would have been a hill, right? Based on where it is geographically.
Well, right. That just proves it all took place in Lithuania because the word for mountain and
the word for hill is exactly the same word, you know, colonists. So I'm just saying, you're going
Now this whole Joseph Smith Eden is...
in Jackson, Missouri. Now, well, you know, a billiard used to be called the Jerusalem of the North.
There you go. So I'm just just putting that out there. Yeah. Okay.
Yes. A little bit more of a hill than a mountain. Okay. Yeah. Right. But it's framed as a
mountain. Why? Well, he's teaching from a mountain. Yeah. Like Moses. People gathered, gathered
around them. Right. Like, like Israel received the Torah. Yeah. I mean, in a real sense, like
And we're going to keep talking about this, but in a real sense, Jesus does what Israel
was always supposed to do. Jesus succeeds where Israel, because he is Israel in this sense.
Right. He is embodying Israel. Yeah, this is Christ is the ultimate triumph of Israel.
So, this is also true.
If we look at the historical experience of Israel as it's shown to us in the Hebrew Scriptures in the Old Testament
We see that the experience of Israel was also profoundly an experience of suffering
Suffering in slavery in Egypt
Suffering at the hands of his brothers
right we see it's kind of literally with Joseph but right later on you have the
Euphria might war, you have these clashes between the Israelite civil war that's related
in the last few chapters of judges, right?
That you have various persecutions of sort of the remnant.
The faithful remnant of Israel gets persecuted by the faithless Israelites, like in the
case of the Prophet Elijah, right?
You also of course have...
See...
Israel suffering at the hands of the foreign nations who attack who invade who harass right who try to conquer
But the key here right because of course we see Christ's experience also as one of
profound suffering right of suffering rejection
alienation mocking right ultimately well several attempts at killing him before
actually he gets betrayed and suffers and dies. Right? Is that the arc of the the hemerous
riftures is about Israel suffering because of her sins?
Right. The reason the Israelite Civil War happens in judges is because of the idolatry and
immorality.
that Israel has fallen into, where they begin to turn on each other.
The division of the kingdom into the Northern and Southern Kingdom is a result of Solomon's sin.
When the Assyrians come and wipe out the Northern Kingdom of Israel, it's for their apostasy and
idolatry and sinfulness.
When...
explicit in the in the scriptures.
Yes, yes, this is read the Old Testament stuff.
This is not so deep exigenical, ledger domain.
Yeah, this is not an interpretation that you have to apply.
The Old Testament interprets this.
Yes, this is this is just the narrative.
Yeah.
When when Babylon comes and conquers Judah and takes them into exile,
it's because of their sin, right?
Yeah.
Again and again and again is suffering for Israel is suffering for her sins.
The difference here is Jesus, when he suffers, it's not because of his sins because he doesn't have any.
Yeah.
And so he's suffering for the people's sins.
He's suffering for Israel's sins.
Right?
And this embodiment of Israel in this way and these ways we've been talking about is,
Again, part and parcel of why they look at Jesus.
is say, this is the Messiah because he is Israel.
And so he is Israel's Messiah.
But this goes even deeper than that.
And to kind of get at how deep it goes,
or to go a little bit deeper down the rabbit hole,
or however we want to frame it,
we're gonna use, there are a lot of texts
from the Old Testament we could read on this.
Right, but we're gonna read one in particular,
It part because I just, it's what I really like.
Yeah, this is a big favorite, big crowd favorite, I think.
Yeah.
And I don't think Father Andrew is going to read it like the Russian way where he goes
up a note every, every time.
But I mean, you're free to do that if you want to, Father Andrew.
You can find that on YouTube, not my voice, mind you.
I actually think there's one of Father's surges, Halverson, doing this on the YouTube's
somewhere who was for...
one semester one of my homolytic professors when I was at St. T. Cans.
He decided he had enough of St. T. Cans and went back to St. Vlats.
Yours I think will be more in the style of plain reading. Yes, yes, correct, right.
There will be no singing tonight. Okay, so yeah, this is Ezekiel chapter 37
verses 1 through 14. The hand of the Lord was upon me and he brought me out in the spirit of the Lord
and set me
down in the middle of the valley, it was full of bones. And he let me around among them
and behold, there are very many on the surface of the valley and behold, they were very dry.
And he said to me, Son of Man, can these bones live? And I answered, Oh Lord God, you know.
Then he said to me, prophesy over these bones and say to them, Oh, dry bones, hear the
word of the Lord. Thus says the Lord God to these bones, behold, I will cause breath to
enter you and you shall live. And I will lay sinews upon you and will cause flesh to
come upon you and cover you with skin and put breath in you and you shall live and you shall
know that I am the Lord. So I prophesied as I was commanded. And as I prophesied there was a sound,
behold, a rattling and the bones came together bone to its bone. And I looked and behold, there were
sinews on them and flesh had come upon them and skinned covered them, but there was no breath in them.
Then he said to me, prophesied to the breath, prophesied son of man and say to the breath, thus says
Lord God come.
from the four winds, O breath, and breathe on these slain that they may live.
So I prophesied as he commanded me, and the breath came into them, and they lived and stood
on their feet and exceedingly great army.
Then he said to me, Son of man, these bones are the whole house of Israel.
Behold, they say, our bones are dried up, and our hope is lost.
We are indeed cut off.
Therefore, I prophesy and say to them, thus says the Lord God, behold, I will open your
graves and raise you from your graves of my people.
people. And I will bring you into the land of Israel. And you shall know that I am the
Lord when I open your graves and raise you from your graves, oh my people. And I will put my
spirit within you and you shall live. And I will place in you your own land, place you in your
own land. Then you shall know that I am the Lord. I have spoken and I will do it to clear
the Lord. And pretty much every Lord there is actually Yahweh there. Yeah. Yeah. Then you
You will know that I am Yahweh.
Yeah.
Right.
And so this is Ezekiel, of course, is a prophet during the exile.
Yeah.
So at the time, Ezekiel is exercising his prophetic ministry.
The northern tribes of Israel are gone from the face of the earth,
right, 150 years before this wiped out by the Assyrians.
Never to come back.
Population distributed through the Assyrian Empire through intermarriage gone.
At the time, Ezekiel is saying this,
Judah is an exile in Babylon, but even when they're allowed to eventually return under Cyrus,
there's still going to be under foreign domination.
They're going to return to become a pro...
of the Persian Empire, which is then going to end up being a province of the
So you could empire, which is then going to end up briefly being an independent
province and then once again right back to province of the Roman Empire.
So they're under foreign domination. So the Israel over which David was king, the
paradigm for the Messiah. The Israel
over which David is king is dead. Yeah, long gone. The dream is dead. And there's no sensible,
visible, non-completely miraculous way that it could come back. It'd be restored. Right,
not in its fullness. Right. There could be a remnant of it, but like this is not going to
actively
come back again. And so the imagery that God uses here, of course, is very pointed. Right?
It's not just like, oh, it's like your debt. No, as Israel, Israel was dead. And the promise
here is that Israel is going to rise again, rise from the debt. This is going to require
the miraculous power of God.
Obviously, right? God is the one who could do this. The fact that he has there, then you will
know that I am Yahweh. Then you will know that I am the one who causes things to be that weren't.
Right? Israel is going to be remade, right? It is died and is going to rise again. One of the
sort of curious things that you find in the Gospels and that you find in St. Paul's epistles.
And in summary of some of the Apostles preaching in Acts even in the New Testament
are statements that Paul goes to a synagogue, say, Paul goes to a synagogue in the book of Acts
and he argues from the scriptures that the Messiah must die and rise again.
Right? And you may have noticed if you...
go back to that episode where we talked about the Messiah and second-tabled Judaism.
That one on anybody's list really.
Yeah, yeah.
I thought the Christ was supposed to, you know, live forever, live forever, right?
Right.
What do you mean he's going to be lifted up?
What do you mean he's going to be crucified?
Wait a minute.
Right.
And this is, I mean, St. Paul confirms this, right?
He says, you know, the message of the cross is a stumbling block to the Jews.
They're like, oh, he's the Messiah.
Oh.
Where is he now? Crucified by the Romans, huh? Right? That's not yeah, right? That's how false Messiah's died in the first century
Right, they got crucified by the Romans, right?
So this was this was not on anybody's list and yet the apostles were making a case
From the Hebrew Scriptures that the Hebrew Scriptures said that
Let the Messiah would die and rise again.
And I think this is the place where we find this.
This is the way that we have to understand this.
That Jesus has the Messiah embodies Israel.
Israel died because of her sins.
Jesus dies with no sins, so he is able to die for her sins.
And then when Jesus rises again as the Messiah,
he's the first fruit, he's the beginning of that promised resurrection and restoration.
And so Jesus participates not only in the suffering that Israel historically suffered,
but also in the death of Israel.
Okay.
Hmm.
Right.
in order that the people of God could participate
in the new life that comes in the resurrection.
And just to head off,
because I do not yet have that better class
of critics that I crave.
Right.
Yes, there's a lot more to say
about Jesus' death and resurrection.
We're not saying that's all.
Yeah, of course.
Right.
Yeah, yeah.
It's, you know, it's kind of sad to me.
I mean I
get it, I get it, right? Because I felt this way at one point in my life when I was a lot younger,
frankly, that you see something really interesting you want to understand what's in the scripture,
you get an answer like, okay, that's it. Good, I got it down now, you know? But if Orthodox
Christianity is the truth, and I believe that it is uniquely the truth, then shouldn't it be so
BORN
that you can never sort of master it, you know, that you can never get it all down.
Like, you know, shouldn't it be so full that it rises to the level of, and beyond, the
level of human dignity in every possible way, you know, that it's a bottomless, bottomless
well.
So yeah, there's so many things one can say about the death and resurrection of death.
and I mean, even Posca itself says so many of them,
but still just begins in some ways, you know.
But this is one of them.
This is one of them.
For sure.
This is one of them that maybe we don't emphasize enough.
And yes, it's true.
It's not just, I mean, it's theologically true.
Right.
Any theological system that explains everything about God
and that you can contain in your human head is wrong.
Yeah.
And probably heretical, but at least...
wrong. But it's not just truth
theologically it's true that the scriptures.
Right? I say this is somebody who
what got a PhD of this. Right?
Like there is not a point that any
human ever reaches where they could
say they understand the scriptures in a
comprehensive way. Right? It doesn't
happen right it doesn't
happen. And that's not just because of our nature as humans. It's so on one level, because
of our nature as humans, right? As you just mentioned, right? You were a younger man once.
I was always old, but the way in which a 21-year-old
Well, a 15-year-old, a 21-year-old, a 30-year-old, a 45-year-old, and then moving on, a 60-year-old,
a 75-year-old who spends time in the Scriptures, hears the same Scriptures, is very different,
not contradictory.
There's not just about like, oh, I understood it wrong before and now I understand it correctly.
God meets you through the Scriptures.
different points in your life. Yeah. And you're able to absorb different things at different
points. And often the stuff you absorb later builds on what you absorbed earlier. Yeah. And
you're different. And the scriptures are not a magic riddle box. Yeah. Okay. They aren't
like opaque. Right. Some of them are difficult. Right. I'm not saying that there aren't difficult
parts of the scriptures.
But you know, a guy stuck in Tulsa, I don't know why I'm picking on Tulsa, but a guy stuck in Tulsa overnight,
who flips open the Gideon Bible in his hotel room because he can't get to sleep and reads the
parable of the Good Samaritan, can get the message that he needs to love his neighbor.
Yeah.
Right.
That's not like, oh no, I need to find some church father to explain this to me, right?
You can get it, right.
But at the same...
time someone who spent their whole life studying the scriptures and is now in their 80s can pick
up and read the parable of the Good Samaritan and have it strike them in all new ways and interact
with their experiences in life in different ways, right, where they learn from it too.
That's how scripture
works. Right? And so in most cases, right, we'll peel back a metal metal layer here on Lord
of Spirits. Right? Most of our episodes, I want to say all, but who knows, right? There's
might be one that's different, but most of our episodes are essentially a trajectory.
Right.
line, we draw a line, a through line, through the scriptures on some topic, right, and
through tradition on some topic. But if you think about, right, a sphere, how many
possible lines you could have go through that sphere. And none of those lines would be
contradicting any of the other ones.
Some of them would intersect.
with each other. Some of them would run parallel to each other for a certain distance, right?
But, right, you could keep doing that forever.
So what we're doing tonight is three closely aligned trajectories that all have to do with what
it means that Jesus is the Messiah. And this is the first one. This idea that Jesus embodies
Israel.
Israel's experience. And even the death and then resurrection of Israel, the restoration,
the destruction and restoration of God's people. And the people who traveled with him and
ate with him and talked with him, even though they're interacting with him as this human,
right? That's how they're interacting with him. That's how they first encountered him.
see this about him and this is one of the things that causes them.
to conclude this is the Messiah.
Yeah, pretty cool.
Well, we still got two more halves to this episode.
So we're going to take our first break
and we'll be right back with the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
4.
Forge enduring connections with Orthodox brothers.
Strengthen your faith.
Be encouraged and challenge yourself at the first ever ancient faith men's retreat.
The retreat features four engaging speakers, daily services and Sunday divine liturgy, fellowship
with like-minded Orthodox men, and more at the beautiful Antiochian Village Conference
Center in Bolivar, Pennsylvania.
Thursday, August 22nd through Sunday, August 25th.
Speakers include Hyromunk Basil of Holy Cross Monastery
in Wayne, West Virginia, Father John Strickland,
author of the Paradise in Utopia Book Series,
Father John Oliver, the host of the AFR podcast,
Hearts and Minds, and Father Michael Mark Antony,
priest at St. John Chrysostom Orthodox Church
in Nashville, Tennessee.
For more information and to register,
please visit store.enginefaith.com slash event.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, welcome back everybody.
If you're just joining us, we are talking about how it is that Peter and I are talking
who knew Jesus in person realized that he was the Messiah.
Not just that he had fulfilled a list of things
that were prophesied about him in the Old Testament,
although of course he did that and is doing that,
but how they recognized him as the Messiah.
And in the first half, we talked about Jesus
as embodying or recapitulating Israel, an Israel story.
And so we've got two other ways that Jesus
um, embody
elements of Israel and we're covering each one of those in these three halves.
So, pretty straight forward episode I think.
Wait a minute.
Wait a recapitulate the first half.
Right.
Just a decent.
Yeah, it's funny, you know, to use both in body and recapitulate because that's head and
body right there.
Yeah.
You know, I said I didn't have the etymology jingle going
head-and-well
his knees and toes. Exactly. Exactly. Well, you know, there's that great phrase. I can't remember
which which work it's in now, but there's that great phrase from St. Augustine in Latin,
totus, christus, kaput at corpus, the whole Christ head and body. And of course, he's as far as
I recall, he's talking about the church when he mentions the body there. But yeah, the whole
Christ, head and body. I feel like we need more songs with hand motion.
That's true. I mean, yeah, this, you know, maybe this is something that the Orthodox Church
could learn from vacation Bible. Oh, no, I just met in the world. Oh, in the world in general.
Yes. Like, I think pop songs need it, not dance crazy. Right. Like TikTok dances. I think
that's passé now, especially since TikTok lost all their music rights. Just hand emotions.
You are an award winning ballroom dancer though, I would love.
to see you start your own TikTok channel.
Well, get used to any music now.
There's probably some public domain.
There is a lot of ballroom dancing music
that is in the public domain.
Yes, true.
Yes, exactly.
I'm sure there's some strouce or whatever,
you could put on.
There's been that out there.
This is what the people want, Father Steven.
I doubt it somehow.
But think of the merch.
I'm not big on the cell in the merch.
I know. I know. I know.
All right. What are we doing?
And in this hat, what are we doing in general?
Yeah. What are we doing?
How have we come to this?
Who am I? What am I?
Senior work. What am I doing?
Yeah. Anyway, existential crisis in the middle of an episode.
Well, it's about time we are in our, you know, late 40s.
So we should be having some existential crazies.
So that's it.
So yeah, so this is, there's a whole bunch of things that I can't do because it would
be a midlife crisis.
It would be a little too cliche.
Right.
Like, I don't know if I'm talking about this.
Like, I have this firm rule that if you don't have any tattoos by the time you're 40,
you could not get any tattoos.
Fair.
If you have gotten tattoos before you're 40, you could keep getting tattoos your whole
life.
Yeah.
But if you hit 40 was zero tattoos.
And then you start getting tattoos, it's a midlife crisis.
And it's just kind of sad.
And people look at you kind of funny.
Noting knowingly, because this is radio,
so they can't say I'm doing that.
So I think this is, there are a number of things
like you can't buy a sports car, right?
Like after a certain age, if you're a dude.
Right? Like women have to be careful
with their hair styles once they're just certain.
You don't want to get the midlife crisis thing going.
Middle ages is the worst of all possible worlds.
You can't get up off the floor,
you don't get senior discounts.
It's true.
Anyway, okay, now that we're done commiserating.
All right.
Welcome back kids.
Back to the show.
Yes, Lipper Stappers, get up my lawn.
We're gonna talk about here the second half.
We're gonna be talking about the way in which
Jesus.
as the Messiah embodies the Torah.
That may already sound crazy to some people.
Yeah.
And I say good.
Yes.
And I say to you.
Good.
So again here, like in the first half, we have to go back and revisit a couple of concepts,
not full on review, but revisit a couple of concepts.
And that's, you know, we're using the term.
Torah very deliberately here rather than other possibilities.
In parts, try to break up connotation.
So we've talked before on the show about how the word Torah and Hebrew
means something like teaching.
And that got translated in the third century, in the
two agent, which is a translation of the Torah as no most
Third century BC by the way everybody.
Third century.
BC. No most see my interest extends not that far into AD. So I just assume. Yeah, no
most meaning kind of way. Yeah, no most kind of was an idea that included like a whole way
of life. A lot of things that we would file under culture, manners, mores, right, a whole
sort of way of life, a way of being in the world. It was a very sort of rich term.
That's their way.
And then when St. Jerome chose Lex to translate that,
Lex and Latin had a richer meaning closer to NoMos,
but ended up coming into English as law.
And then the term law even got kind of devalued in English
to the point that now when we hear the word law,
even when it's used like in the New Testament,
We think.
of like commandments, like law or like legal codes. Yeah. Yeah. And it's very obvious that
the Torah includes, for example, the book of Genesis, which doesn't include any of that.
Yep. And the narrative fortunes of Exodus and the narrative fortunes of the other,
the other books of the Torah, right? And so we're using Torah here because what we're talking
about his more than just rules. And that immediately
becomes important that idea that it's not just rules, commandments, laws.
When we talk about what it means to fulfill the Torah and we've talked about in the past,
that the way a lot of people use fulfill the law or interpret fulfill the law when it
occurs to the New Testament is basically get rid of right.
So, it's used as this weird sort of linguistic ledger domain where, you know, Christ says
he came not to abolish the law but to fulfill it.
So someone will say, you know, oh, see?
So we don't follow this that and the other from the Torah anymore, right?
You say to them, but Christ didn't come to abolish the law.
They're like, no, he fulfilled it.
And the result is the same.
We could ignore it now.
We're ahead for using-
the word fulfill, but we mean abolish. Yeah, it's out of dice. So it's just sort of this trick.
Like no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, we're not firing you. We're letting you go.
Good luck in your future. Late off. Yeah.
And relatedly then, some people will interpret this and say, well, Jesus fulfills.
the law to mean, oh, well, he kept the rules, right? He didn't break any of the rules,
which, okay, true, right? Jesus did keep the commandments, right? All of them. But that's
a very base level of what we're talking about when we're talking about him fulfilling
the Torah. Yeah, Torah is way bigger than the command. Yeah, it's
So the actual meaning of the word fulfill, as we've said before, is sort of right there
in it.
And that's that it's being to be filled full, right?
Filled up to overflowing.
Yeah.
And I should say, by the way, that if you understand this correctly, then you can start
to see why it is, for instance, that there are a number of commandments even in ordinances
and specific things that God tells Israel to do in the Torah that are said in the text.
itself to be forever. Right? This shall be, you know, an ordinance forever. Right? And yet you'd be
like, well, wait a minute. Nobody's doing that anymore. And what sense is that forever? You know,
like Christians don't do that. Even modern rabbinic Jews don't do that thing, whatever it might be,
especially some of the sacrificial stuff. But if you understand how Jesus is the one who embodies
and fulfills the Torah. Then you start to see
why it's forever. Right. Right. Right. And so that's part of explaining what that means. Yeah.
Because that's a question I at least get a lot. Yeah. Yeah. Right. Like, okay. So fulfill means
fills up to overflowing. How does Jesus fill the Torah up to overflowing? Right. What does that
actually mean? And so that that's part of what we're going to be getting at here. Yes. Yes.
in this half, right? And so what we have presented in the Torah, the
first five books of the Bible, a Pentateuch.
We have presented is a way of life,
a way of being in the world.
That's why no most was a good translation.
So that takes different forms.
So in Genesis and the other narrative material
where we're talking about the lives of people,
we're seeing a way of life described narratively.
and that's described both positively and negatively.
Right? So there are positive descriptions of things that conform to that way of life, like
Isaac and Rebecca's marriage. Right? There are also descriptions of things that deviate
from that way of life, like various incidents of polygamy. And you see in those narratives
How that goes wrong, right?
How that goes badly.
The fruit and the...
results that that produces. Right. Both of those are ways of using narrative to describe a
correct, a correct way of life. Right. You have on the one hand, exemplars, you have models,
right, to follow. On the other hand, you have cautionary tales. Right. This is what happens when you go
when you go the other way. And it should go without saying, and I'm sure we've said this on the show
before. Right.
but a lot of people have problems with this.
A lot of our atheist friends have problems with this.
Just because the Bible describes something happening
that doesn't mean the Bible is saying that it's good.
I know, and you can tell the people are trying to make
that claim when they talk about, for instance,
quote unquote, biblical marriage.
Yeah.
That's often where the thing that they'll throw out,
oh, listen, you want to talk about biblical marriage?
We'll look at all these marriages in the Old Testament.
Look at me.
Jesus God didn't say to do that.
Yes, yes. And in fact, if you read the narrative, it goes horribly wrong.
Yes.
It's like, workout well for you.
Like, Deuteronomy says the king should not multiply wives. David then has a whole bunch
of wives. Look what happens in David's family.
Yeah.
Right. And if, again, I have to just read it out of the service. David says all of this
stuff that's happening in my family is because of my sin.
David says that in the text of
Scripture, right? Not even, you know, any deep level of interpretation. So yeah, so both
of these occur, right? When you read about what happens with Jacob's family because of
being married to Leia and Rachel and having children with two of his servants, right?
and everything that unfolds, you see, oh,
polygamy is bad.
All right, like this is...
what any sensible person would conclude. But so this way of life, right? And we see,
usually it's in the life of the same person, like in the patriarchal narratives, right?
You see where Abraham does right and where Abraham goes wrong. Right? We see both, right?
And we see Abraham grow through those experiences, right? And grow closer to God by following
in a way.
life. Commandments obviously fitted to that in a very obvious way. Right. So commandments
it's a vote in Hebrew give you the fences. Right. So if we're talking about a way of life away,
we're talking about a road. Right. A road you're going to travel down.
One road is supposed to another road. Right. This is the good road that leads to the place you want to go.
right, one of the
ways that you're kept on the road is if there are established fences, right, without fences,
without any kind of barriers or markers at the edges of the road, you might have a muddy
track. You can't tell is the road continuing this way or that way, right? You might get lost,
might wander off the road.
If you have these clear markers of where the edges of the road are, that won't happen.
They help keep you on the road.
That's how the commandments function.
Right.
They're the borders.
They're the edges that you don't want to wander past.
Right.
This is really the same way that a theological dogma works in the Orthodox church, by the way.
The word dogma in
Greek refers to a boundary marker for somebody's property.
Right.
So the statements of the Ecumenical Council are putting
in these fences, these markers of the edges.
You don't want to go further than this in this direction
or further than that in that direction.
Right.
You want to stay within these boundaries, right,
that mark off the way of salvation.
But this is...
built on how the Torah structures it.
Right. And so, within those, whether it's commandments, whether it's narrative
elements, right, whatever genre we're talking about, what's really being laid out as a way of
understanding the world, a way of seeing the world, a way of reasoning about the world.
And that's obvious, that obviously includes ethical or moral reasoning.
What should I do in this situation?
What is the right thing to me?
What is the thing to do in this situation that will please God, that will bring me closer
to God?
But it includes a lot more, right?
How do we see other people?
How do we see events in the world, right?
How do we understand things that happen to us and that we encounter in our lives?
It is this overarching framework, right?
Right, I've had to see the world.
interact with the world, be in the world, travel through the world toward God.
And so when we talk about Jesus embodying that, hopefully that idea starts to make a lot more sense.
Yeah. That when His disciples, when other people encounter Jesus during His ministry,
They see that he embodies the...
that way of life, that he embodies that way of seeing the world,
that way of seeing others, that way of communicating,
that way of teaching, right?
And, you know, and an awful lot of the gospels, right?
And awful lot of the gospels is Jesus teaching.
And I know there's people out there like, yeah, right?
So, but this is counterintuitive from a lot of theological perspectives.
Right?
So, I'll give an example.
Back during the last quest for the historical Jesus, may it rest in peace, I never know.
Is that still a thing?
No.
Yeah.
The third quest for the historical Jesus is now over.
We don't need a fourth.
Right.
Another one is...
finally dropped the ring into the new. So that's over, but rested pieces, right?
The during that, when you would read these books, as was my want,
didn't matter who it was, those who have stayed matter for this crossing or Robert Funker,
Marcus Borg.
Any of these guys?
Bart Irman's brief
with it before he moved on to other things.
Even into your right stuff, which is much better than most of that other stuff I just named.
Any of that stuff.
Something almost all of them would say interestingly,
was the gospels are basically extended introductions to the Passion narrative.
Well, and they would say in any given gospel about one third of it is passion there. Now, that's less than the majority allowed me to go out.
Right. But coming from a particular theological perspective, which predominates in Western European countries, people get mad now when we talk about Western things in the West.
But
uh, West predominates in Western European countries and uh, their former colonies. Um,
that's the important part.
Right. Jesus dying and rising again, that's the important part. And yeah, we read about his
birth at Christmas and then there's this other stuff in between. Yeah, I mean, this is,
this, this, this is the world of people for whom the only feasts on the church calendar are
Christmas and Easter.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. But so this really important part is the death address or extra
prize. Yeah. And that's something for that. It's really just building up for
that. It's like Jesus predicting that, you know, like that kind of thing. And then
there are all kinds of variants of this, right? So you've got certain types of
dispensationalism that say all that teaching of Jesus isn't for Christians. Oh yeah. I
Enough, right?
about that. I'm like, wait, what? What? Yeah. So that's not even four Christians. So you could
ignore that. Just go straight to death and resurrection because that is for us. Right. And it's
said, there's various versions of this. But but that's sort of the main event. Right. And this
other stuff is sort of and you know, you've got certain species of Protestantism where, you know,
we don't want to look at that stuff. Jesus is teaching too much because it might start looking like
works righteousness right? These tell me to do good things and not do bad things and
You know, that's the worst thing you can do as a Christian.
So yeah, so there's all kinds of reasons why I get sidelined, but it's most of the gospels.
Yeah, yeah, how about it's all important? Yeah. And, and if you're on any kind of
election, I'm going to just talk about the Orthodox election area now, Orthodox election area,
Roman Catholic election area, Protestant election areas, right? How much of the year are you reading
from J-
Jesus teaching and how much of the year you're reading about his death and resurrection.
Yeah, exactly.
Right.
So this is in the structure of the church's worship too, the importance of this material
of Jesus teaching.
Okay.
Now that I've gone there, let me push a little further, Jesus is teaching Torah the whole
time.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, in most ways, there's
There's not really any new material there exactly, which is probably why so many people called
him rabbi.
Yeah.
You know, so the first people who identified him as the Messiah were the people who heard
him teaching.
Yeah, they didn't say.
And heard him teaching.
Well, watch him fulfilling prophecies.
I know it's, these are the things he says.
Right.
And no man ever spoke like this man.
Yes.
he's going in.
He's answering questions, right?
And he's doing this.
And he's arguing with, when he's arguing with the Pharisees,
he's arguing Torah with them, right?
They come and say, why are you healing this person on the Sabbath?
And he says to them, on the Sabbath, if you're,
if your donkey falls into ditch, you pull it out of the ditch.
This is a human, right?
He's arguing from the Torah, right?
Bye.
Yep.
And again, and again, he says to them, you guys claim to be the ones who know Torah.
You're the teachers of the law.
You're the teachers of Torah.
You guys are the ones going out teaching Torah.
But you're not doing it.
You're not living it.
You don't understand it.
You don't know how to apply it to people's lives who come to you.
and what everyone observes about Jesus is the opposite.
that he's living it out, that he's explaining it, that he's teaching it. Right? He's explaining
it since it and this is not so there's this there's this weird idea. There's this weird
idea that there's a couple related. One of them is that Jesus somehow makes the Torah
more difficult.
Right, like he heightens the Torah.
Like, you know what he says, you have heard it say that she'll not murder, but if you
hate your brother, you've already murdered him in your heart.
But somehow like before Jesus said that, it was okay to hate your brother in your heart
as long as you didn't kill him.
That's a really weird way of reading the commandments man.
I'm pretty sure nobody...
No Jewish teacher before Jesus would have told you it's okay to hate your brother and wish him dead
Yeah, just don't actually kill him that otherwise. Yeah, or or the you know
the other one right
Basically like you know if you see a woman and lust after you're in heart and you're her and your heart, you know
Yeah, it's the same as basically if you committed adultery whether it's not like in the Torah.
look but don't touch was the rule. Yeah, yeah. In fact, remember that whole don't
covet your neighbor's wife thing. Oh, I've heard of that. Yeah. That's in there.
The same place is the thou shalt not commit adultery. In fact, just a couple verses later.
Yeah. Yeah. So Christ is again, not making it more difficult. He's applying it correctly.
Right? He's talking about what it actually...
means because all that stuff I once had somebody I will not name them. This is an
Orthodox person. This is an ortho member of the Orthodox clergy. Say to me, we
don't follow the Torah anymore. We follow the commandments of Jesus to love the
Lord your God with all your heart, soul, mind and strength that to love your
neighbors yourself.
To which I responded, those
from Deuteronomy and Leviticus. Those are literally commandments from the Torah.
Yeah. Yeah. Right. And if you notice the reaction, right, we need to watch the reaction
is Jesus is teaching. Right. When Jesus says these things about the Torah, the people look
at him and say.
This must be the Messiah, right?
Because of how he understands and teaches the Torah.
And his enemies, the ones who don't like him,
and who don't think he's the Messiah, what happens?
They're put to shame because they can't argue with him.
Because he understands the Torah better than they do.
That's something to do with him giving it, but we'll get there.
Right?
That's...
He understands it better than they do.
That's what's going on
and all these teaching sections of the Gospels.
Right, and it's going on right there on the surface.
Right.
And it doesn't just,
and this embodying of the Torah doesn't just include.
It does include,
but it isn't just about his teaching.
Christ obviously also lives that way of life as well.
Yeah.
He walks the walk.
We'll get more to that in a minute.
Yeah, but, right?
So yes, Jesus does all the things.
that are commanded in the Torah, he doesn't do the things that are forbidden in the Torah.
Right.
But you look at his criticism of the Pharisees.
Every time he criticizes the Pharisees, he doesn't criticize them for being wrong.
He doesn't say, oh no, you've got this wrong.
Yeah.
He calls the people with you.
hypocrites.
Yeah.
You know, you say the right things, but you're not living it, buddy.
Right.
You're not living it.
You're not...
living it. That's always the criticism, right, that that Jesus is saying, understanding
the Torah, understanding what God's teaching means, living this out, not just memorizing
it, not just, you know, being able to make convoluted arguments about it and win arguments
about it. Right. It's not just about owning the Sadducees. Yeah. There's something to say
about this in terms of Christian...
theology, including Orthodox theology. Right? It's not just about memorizing canons and stuff
from church councils and where to put the right preposition in your Christological statements.
So you're not a heretic and then going out to own other people and win arguments. Right?
That's not how theology works. You're supposed to live it out. Right? You're supposed to live it out.
And when you're actually living it out, the way the saints do
That's why they're saints. They're saints because of how they live their lives.
Some of them are not formally educated, right?
But they lived it out and because they lived it out, they understood it.
Yeah, right. And could explain it. It doesn't work the other way.
But so this is what has now all of this that I've been saying, this episode is going to be great,
Thank you very much.
because I'm anticipating being called
both a Judaizer and an anti-Semite after that.
So by some of the same people.
But that's right.
But this isn't just me going on this wacky,
heberfile, right, tack.
This is, we've fairly recently,
at least as we're doing this live broadcast,
Celebrate it a couple of...
feasts in the life of the Orthodox Church. The feasts of Christ's circumcision and most recently
Christ's presentation in the temple or the meeting of the Lord in the temple when he was brought
40 days after his birth to the temple. And if you read any, any of the hemnography, any of the readings
we've been reading. Okay, from the Orthodox Manet. It's all about Christ's keeping the Torah.
It's all about Jesus keeping the Torah.
It's all over the text, it's everywhere.
Yeah.
It's the whole point of these feasts, right, is to make this point to us, right, that
Jesus is the one who embodies the Torah in this way.
Okay.
something, right? That's some weird thing of mine. Right?
So this carries over, right?
I'll go so far as to say, this is where most modern people fail to understand St. Paul.
When he talks about how to live.
Now that part of St. Paul gets marginalized anyway.
In our modern world, right?
There's this hole.
section of every one of his epistles. He usually follows him saying the word therefore,
where he starts talking to people about how to live, and those parts get a lot less emphasis.
Like after Romans chapter 11, a lot of people just sort of check out.
But for him, this is where he's going with the whole letter.
Right?
And...
And he structures it based on this, based on the way in which Jesus embodied the Torah.
Right.
This is how he understands the Torah relating to the Christian life.
So for St. Paul, there's two ways you can walk.
Right.
that walk language is important because...
in Jewish circles already in the first century AD,
when the Pharisee like St. Paul
is discussing the way people should live
or answering questions as a teacher
about the way he should live.
As he does in his epistles all the time,
here's what you should do.
You should be doing this and not doing that, right?
That whole area of discussion within Judaism
was already called Hawa.
Yeah.
which as I just learned, I mean I knew the word, like I knew that it was like about applying
the Torah, you know, but it means to walk. I mean, yes, it's from the verb to walk the way you walk it.
So, you know, St. Paul's epistles are written in Greek. So when we see the verb to walk, we don't
necessarily, we just think of it as a metaphor or something and we don't make this connection.
right but for him there are two different ways and this is picking up on things in
proud.
There's the way of wisdom, the way of foolishness, the way of life, the way of destruction.
But for St. Paul, there's two ways.
You can walk according to the Spirit and follow the Spirit, meaning capital S Spirit, the Holy Spirit.
The Spirit of God.
Or you can walk according to the flesh.
And if you walk according to the flesh, what that means is that you are living your life
it away where you're seeking to gratify.
your desires. Lust, gluttony, greed, pride, you name it, right? That's what you're seeking to
gratify. If you're walking according to the Spirit, the Holy Spirit, the Spirit of God, then
you're living your life in a way that seeks to please God. But what we see again and again,
It's a Paul explicitly saying is that he's teaching, walking in the way of the Spirit
as a positive way of living and saying that if you live in this way and you follow the
Spirit, then those guardrails from the commandments, it's not that they're not there anymore, right?
But it's that you won't need them.
You will stay on the path.
You're not gonna be belt.
off of them, right? So he lists the fruits, fruit of the spirit,
in Galatians, love joy, peace, patience, kindness, goodness,
faithfulness, gentleness, self-control, right? He says,
against such things, there is no law. There's no commandment
in the Torah that you will violate if your life is filled
with those things. Yeah, because if you become the kind of
a person that the Torah...
trying to get you to be, then you don't actually then have to keep around a rulebook with you.
Oh wait, I got to make sure, don't, don't, you know, kill my, don't commit murder. Okay,
let me keep her. Yeah, I remember.
Have to take over many murders.
No, you don't have to think. Yeah, yeah. If you love your brother, you're not going to think about
killing him right right right in Romans right
say Paul says, right, that they need to learn to love your neighbor. He says, because the one who loves keeps the whole Torah.
Yeah.
If you truly love your neighbor and love God, not, oh, that's it. You know, you've kept the whole Torah. Boom.
But you will not violate it. Yeah. Right. Yeah.
You all right?
And one could ask them like, well, what's the point of the tour than anyway?
Like, I'm a loving person.
Why do I need all that?
Well, it's because number one, like let's be honest with ourselves,
in many ways we are not loving persons, right?
Speak for yourself.
I mean, that's, yeah, I am speaking for myself.
But I know you a little bit, too.
Man, I'm not the light.
But anything.
But I, you know, I think a similar
that works here is being a musician, right? So when you, you know, kids, when you're first
taking those first piano lessons or you're getting out that clarinet for the first time or
whatever it might be, you have to look at the keys and say, okay, when I press this one,
it's A, when I press this one, it's B, C sharp, whatever, right? You know, these together
there's this chord, and so it's very, you're thinking about all of it as you go.
Like you're thinking about the structure, you're thinking about the names of everything,
you're thinking about the rules, how this is work, what exactly is a key change, you
know, all this stuff, right?
But like if you were to go up to Miles Davis, right after he played, you know, some piece
of jazz and say, okay, now what exactly were you doing just now?
He probably would not have explained it in terms of all the stuff that I just said.
because he mastered that a long, long time ago.
He just gets up there and he plays.
And what comes out is music, right?
And in a very real sense, that's how the Torah works.
Is it functions as St. Paul puts it, a tutor, it's a teacher.
It teaches you how to put all these things together, and then you become the person who
can simply do that.
And you don't have to be looking up the rules all the time.
until we're really able to play.
so to speak, then we do need to have the rules.
And, you know, if you make a mistake,
when you're playing a particular piece of music,
you go back and you look at the sheet music
and you say exactly where did I go wrong?
How did I fail here, right?
So even if you do become a decent musician,
you still need to be drilled with the rules every so often
so that you can gain greater perfection.
Right, right.
And this is how this connects to the idea
of having the mind.
of Christ, right, to see the world, right, to in this way, right, ultimately what St. Paul argues
is that in the way that Jesus as the Messiah embodied the Torah, right, that because we have the
Holy Spirit, the Spirit of God dwelling in us, we can now, if we follow the Spirit, live similarly,
Right.
It's not imitate Christ in a wooden sense.
Yeah.
Right.
It is in an external sense.
It is that we will naturally begin to learn to live that way.
Right.
The problem with trying to keep the Torah in his past, that St. Paul identifies, is that
he was trying to keep it externally.
was trying to keep it as rules, just checking off the rules.
And again and again he failed. Right? Because of sin. Was it a problem with the Torah?
It was a problem with him. But that the Holy Spirit now dwelling within him would allow him to keep the Torah.
And if you have any doubts about how I'm reading St. Paul here, I heard you read St. John
Christophe's commentary on Romans where he says the same thing.
That's as much as I'm allowed to quote church fathers.
There's an episode of Lord Jesus.
No.
So I will let it go.
All the new kids are not going to get these jokes.
Yeah.
I also want to add because we kind of glossed over it.
We have a very weird mental image of Jesus.
Jesus a lot of the time.
time. Because we've gotten it from a lot of frankly, I'll speak for myself growing up
in the United States, bad Protestant art and movies about Jesus. Man, are you disson
the flannel graph? No, not the flat of graph. I'm talking about the illustrations in those
Bible story books and stuff. Yeah. Yeah. He's always got like a white one piece tunic
and then I'll...
red sash. Yeah. What is that always about? I don't know. But for the record, when we say
Jesus kept the commandments, those were the commandments about dress too. Yeah. And about what he ate.
Jesus was Jewish, sorry to bring it to you, Greeks. Right. He dressed as a Jewish man was supposed to.
He presented himself as it.
as a Jewish man was supposed to. He ate, right? As the Torah said, one should eat, right?
He kept the whole Torah. So, right, when he, for example,
criticizes the Pharisees for their tassels, he doesn't criticize them for wearing tassels
at the edge of their garments. They were supposed to do that in the Torah. He criticized them
for making the tassels long and the factories broad and big, meaning doing it in a way that
it was clearly intent.
to attract other people's attention and to make you look pious to other people. That's what he criticized.
Right. Because that was a hypocritical way of keeping Torah. That's not why God gave the Torah,
was so that you could make yourself look really pious to other people and become proud.
Right. But yeah, keep that in mind, right? Just your mental image of Jesus look remotely Jewish.
If not, probably need some correction, but...
Yeah. Exactly. So, yeah, I mean, the point of all of this is, you know, and we talked
about this a little bit, and I should say extensively actually, but we have the mind
of Christ episode, you know, and that is to gain this sense of understanding, interpreting,
applying the Torah the way that Christ himself does. And as we've said in this half, as
he embodies.
My key is, in a sense, the living Torah.
You know, so.
All right, well, we're gonna take our second and final break
and we'll be right back with a third half
of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855 AF Radio.
Now, either Duman, Light a lamp and put it under a bushel, but on a lamp stand, and it
gives light unto all that are in the house.
Matthew 515
Ancient Faith's lamp stand institute is an introductory media training forum for Orthodox
Christians aged 18-23 who are interested in learning skills in digital media and applying
them to the service of the church.
July 8th.
18th to the 21st, a group of 10 students will be gathered at the ancient faith ministry's
headquarters in Chesterton, Indiana, to learn the essentials of podcasting and video production.
The weekend will include ins and outs of live radio production, video production and
concept, marketing what you make, and the future of Orthodox media.
There will also be open work sessions for recording radio material, refining a personal
project and preparing a live radio broadcast.
For more information, visit store.ancientfaith.com slash events.
Are you?
Yes, why can't I learn digital media skills?
You're too old, man.
It's ageism.
Yep.
Old dog, new tricks, not a thing.
Look, nobody who's heard any of my podcasts needs that me knows that I need to learn podcasting
skills.
Look, you come up here.
I'll show you a couple things, okay?
Yeah.
You're old too.
I know.
But see, unlike you, I didn't get this in as my bit life crisis.
I need the zoomers to show me how to use the computers.
That's what I need.
I feel they don't want to.
Yes, it can happen for you, man.
Yes.
Well, welcome back.
We're talking about how it is that people who met Jesus,
how did they identify Him as the Messiah,
even though they weren't sitting there with a whole list of things from
the Old Testament saying,
aha, aha, He did this, He fulfilled that.
How did they recognize him in-
their direct encounter with him as the Messiah. And in the first half, we talked about Christ as
embodying Israel, embodying Israel's story, the second as Christ, embodying the Torah. And
what's this one about Father Stephen? This is about the way in which Jesus as the Messiah embodies
Israel's God. Here we go. And so again, right, to clarify.
What we're going to be talking about here is we've done a lot about Christology, obviously,
in various episodes of this show.
We had the whole series on Christ and the Old Testament.
We have talked about recently Christ's The Divine Logos and Wisdom and Proverbs.
All of those are approaching Christology,
basically sort of top down.
So we're talking about the divine person
who then is made flesh, right?
And that fact.
So we're gonna be talking in a sense talking
about Christology now, right?
In the way that Jesus is the Messiah and bodies
that got of Israel,
but we're gonna be coming at it from the opposite side.
Right? So, when the disciples first encountered Jesus, when the people who Jesus preached to,
first encountered him. The people of Jerusalem first saw him and heard him and encountered
him. They encountered him as human. That was their immediate experience.
Yeah, I mean, he was frankly not walking around, transfigured with the uncreated light most
to the right. Right. That happened once briefly in front of
three disciples. The rest of the time, as people interacted with him, they were interacting
with him as a human. Nevertheless, some of them came to the conclusion that this person,
Jesus who we've met, who we've eaten meals with, who we've sat with.
who we've slept next to while we were traveling overnight.
Embodies the God of Israel in a new unique way.
And
this theologically has to do with
Christ's humanity as the veil.
Right.
When we say that, some people are thinking, Oh, veil like it's hidden,
like Christ's humanity hides who he really is.
That's not what we're saying, right?
Because Christ's humanity is also who he really is.
That's right.
But it is the veil in the sense of the veil
that separated the Holy of Holies from the Holy place.
Yeah, and that was it there to keep people
from looking inside.
Right, that was there to keep people from dying.
Right.
They wouldn't experience that whole death by holiness thing
by entering into the presence of God in an unworthy manner.
Right. Right. And so there is a day when God will reveal himself
and visit his people. That's called the day of the Lord. That's judgment day.
Right. Yes, that is coming. I mean, it's interesting about right because
sometimes people will say, well, why doesn't God just reveal
Himself to me? Why does he just reveal Himself to the world?
Like what's with all the hiding? You know, so you don't die.
Yeah, it's so you don't die. I mean, I get the question, I get it,
I get it, you know, seeing as believing in all that, but it really is
because we would, we would suffer the consequences. You become
responsible for whatever you receive. So God's hit
this is actually a mercy and it's his patience so that we have time to repent.
Right. So that's what the veil is about. Right. And so Christ's humanity is serving as this veil.
Right. In that kind of protective way. Right. But it doesn't stop people.
Does it stop faithful people? People who are paying attention. Right. People who are listening.
Christ from realizing that
he is embodying the God of Israel.
And so what do we mean by that,
other than just an ontological claim?
Like, he'll be like, okay, yeah, Jesus is God.
Well, that's not just what we're saying.
Right?
Because we're being more particular than that.
He embodies the God of Israel, the God who we see
in the Hebrew scriptures and the Old Testament.
Right, a particular got.
There's not a lot of value in generic God.
There's zero value in Plato's God.
Right.
My definition.
So if there was
just contemplates himself, if there was, for example,
some guy who called himself a Christian apologist on the West Coast, who was a
reticle on every single topic of doctrine,
it's been most of his time just trying to argue with atheists that some kind of God
exists. That would be of no value.
Hypothetical.
Shade thrown three times.
That's two times out of the west for you.
Yes.
So we are, we're talking about the true and living God, a very particular God, the real God,
who is embodied by Jesus as the Messiah.
And so what are...
some of the elements that characterize the God we see in the Hebrew scriptures in the
Old Testament that we also see in Jesus, because Hebrews will say Jesus is the express image
of his character.
This is it.
So what is that character?
of the first elements.
that's present all through the Hebrew Scriptures
of the Old Testament is the humility of God,
which is a strange phrase probably to most people,
especially our Calvinist friends who believe
what God is all about is glorifying himself.
But in actuality, we see over and over again
in the Hebrew Scriptures of the Old Testament
the humility of God.
We see that over against other
gods, right? When you compare him with the gods of the nations are always proclaiming,
they're always glorifying themselves, are always proclaiming, you know, how great and how
powerful and wonderful they are. Sometimes too comedic effect, now that no one is worshiping them
anymore when we find the old tablets, right? There's sort of an osamandious thing going on with some of
with them.
But what do we see with the God of Israel with the true God?
He will, for example, identify himself as the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob.
We hear that all the time.
We're used to hearing that.
God is the God of Abraham and of Isaac and of Jacob.
And we don't think every time God says that to identify himself, he's saying, I am the
God of three generations of nomadic Bedouins.
Yeah.
Right. That's not that big of a brag. Yeah, not superpressive in the ancient world. Right.
Compared to the gods of Egypt, the gods of the Babylonian Empire, the gods at right.
Three generations of nomadic Bedouins.
Right. This is what we're getting at when we talk about the humility of God.
Right. The way that God
comes down to meet humanity and thereby elevates humanity. Right.
Particular human persons. God identifies himself as the protector of orphans and widows and the poor.
All those people who have no rights and no one to stand up for them. Right.
God sends Moses and Aaron to Pharaoh and he identifies himself as the
God of the Hebrews and Pharaoh picks up on this pretty quickly. He's like, oh, the God of a bunch of slaves.
Yeah. The God of losers is basically the way that he takes it. You know, yes.
Like he's like, well, whoever your God is, since I've enslaved you,
mine must be better. And in Pharaoh's case, you know, he thought he was one himself. So,
right?
it. Like this is this is not normal.
the relationship world. For a God, let alone the most high God, the God who created everything
to choose to identify himself and who he would identify himself with. And we also have to
be honest, even when he's the God of Israel, right, or the God of Judah, we have been brought
up right culturally even
Even if we weren't brought up in a Christian environment per se,
or a Jewish environment per se,
we're brought up in a culture that's deeply informed by the Bible.
And so we have this greatly outsized sense
of how important Israel as a kingdom was.
Because it's so central to the Old Testament
to the Hebrew Scriptures.
But if we're just going by objective quote unquote, geopal
material level archaeology. Right. Then we're talking about a kingdom that existed as a United Kingdom.
For like a hundred years. Yeah, it's not in world history. Right. It's not one of the great empires of old.
It was regional, a little bit more than tribes, but yeah.
After that hundred years it broke in two.
One half of it lasted another 175 years and then was gone, never to return.
That was the one named Israel by the way.
So there was a nation in the world called Israel before 1948, for about 275 years in all
of human history.
And did you know that didn't conquer that?
that much territory, you know.
Yeah, due to gets 135 more years.
Yeah, that's right.
Yeah, some territory.
About 400.
But you know, this is not some big empire, whatever.
And as far as world history is concerned,
Israel's not a big deal in the ancient world.
Yes, yes.
I dare say, and as much as this may annoy our Jewish friends,
if it weren't for Christianity,
It would be a-
know. If it weren't for Christianity, incorporating the Hebrew scriptures into Christianity's Bible
and then Christianity spreading through the whole world, you would know about as much about
ancient Israel slash Judah as you know about the Hittites or the Lovians.
tough but fair. Yeah that's right so geopolitically on the stage of the world.
insignificant nation. God nonetheless identifies himself as the God of Israel.
Yeah. The God. Just to give you some sense of what this might be like, everybody. And I'm not,
I'm not throwing shade on what in this podcast has been referred to in the past as the poor man's
Ohio, but it'd be like saying it's it's the God of Indiana. Yeah, you know, like, I mean, I love
love Indiana, you know, whatever, but, but no one's like saying, oh.
Indiana, you know, they're, that's a very threatening place, you know, they're going to take over Illinois, you know, like it's not, it's, it's not, it's not, we love you.
Indiana get ready for shots fired. It's like the God of Lithuania.
What?
Well, the God of Netherlands, very tall, but very,
Yes, very tall and very blonde.
But up to that.
Blond and blunt.
Problem.
Handsome. Yeah. So, yeah. Right. So, but this is this is the God who we meet in the Hebrew scriptures.
Right. We meet the Hebrew scriptures. A God who has who created everything, created every human,
and created every nation, but chooses to identify himself with the weak, the powerless, right?
With...
with Bedouins, with short-lived kingdoms
out of his love and out of his humility.
And of course, we see this reflected
in the life of Jesus right from the beginning.
You have the circumstances of his birth,
both in the sense of being born in a cave
that was used as a stable and being
setting an animal food trough.
for a crib, right, and living in dirt poverty and in Nazareth, right.
His father was basically a day like St. Joseph was a day laborer who did like fix it jobs for other
peasants who were poor to pay him. But also there are clear indications in the Gospels. This isn't
just something that comes.
later in Hellmoody Judaism or something, that there were people at the time who made accusations
about the circumstances of his birth. These people who didn't believe Jesus was the Messiah did not
believe in the Virgin birth, folks. They thought there was something fishy, and you get things like,
in St. John's Gospel, a bunch of Jewish people who are arguing with him, just saying to Jesus,
We know who our father is.
That's not coincidental. God forgive them. For that blasphemy. Jesus was not born in the
Son of Herod or the Son of the Emperor. He was not. And the poverty isn't just something
in terms of his birth and early life, right?
He never owned.
a place to live. He never owned more than the clothes on his back. He traveled from place to
place homeless. He would either someone would offer him hospitality or he and the disciples would
sleep outside. When they journeyed around, that's why we see them over in the Gospels, sleeping on
boats. Yeah, they don't own fishing boats, just wherever they were. Not settled in one place.
So then of course, ultimately the ultimate display.
Christ's humility is submitting himself to suffering and death,
and a particularly not just painful but shameful and humiliating death.
And so the humility that's seen in the life of Jesus is the perfect reflection of the humility of God,
of the God of Israel that we see in the Hebrew Scriptures.
This.
This embodying of the God of Israel also ties into what we were talking about in the
second half.
Not just that Jesus embodies the Torah, but Jesus also teaches it.
He is the giver of it.
And the way that he gives it, the way that he teaches it, the centrality of love in
his teaching at his message, which by the way is also the central
of the book of Deuteronomy. The fifth book of the Torah of the Pentateuch. Right.
Follows this pattern of God who gave it in the first place. Right. And it's very important
that another way in which related to the Torah, Jesus embodies the God of Israel, is that just like
at Mount Sinai. When the Torah was given through Moses, Moses comes
comes down, reads the book of the covenant to the people and the people say, oh yeah,
all that you've said, we're going to do that.
Yes.
And then they do none of that, right?
Yeah.
Right?
In the same way, right?
Christ comes and lives out and expresses and teaches the Torah and communicates this
way of life to people and they reject it.
This is...
the whole arc of the Hebrew Scriptures.
Right, from the narrative portions that show it to the prophets who explain it this way,
is God coming, condescending in His humility to love Israel and Israel rejecting Him.
And God being faithful to Israel and Israel being faithless.
That's the whole story.
of the Hebrew Scriptures. This is not me insulting Jewish people, right? This is their Bible. This is,
yeah, I mean, I know a couple of miles. Right? This is the arc of the Hebrew Scriptures. And we see
that arc in the life of Jesus. Right? We see that arc of the life of Jesus. He came to his own and
in his own received him not. Right? He comes as he was and they reject him. Right? And this way in with
the blessings of God get repaid with faithfulness and betrayal in the Old Testament and the teaching and the
miracles done by Christ get repaid with rejection and attack right and and suffering in the life of Jesus as the Messiah
right. This becomes a subject of meditation in a lot of our Holy Week texts a lot of our Holy Week
chimnography. Is METIT-
on how this relationship between Jesus and his people mirrors parallels and bodies the relationship between God and his people.
Right.
And so we've got examples.
Yes indeed.
So, yes, in a holy week, there are...
Well, a lot of them. But we're going to read one of them from more than three. Yes, more than three. How about that? Yes.
Yeah, just go to church a lot during Holy Week people. Just just go to church. Just take the week off and go to everything.
It's the only way to live.
Anyway, in the service of royal hours, which is celebrated on Holy Friday morning.
One of the hymns from royal hours goes like this.
When thou was led to the cross, Lord, thou didst say,
For what act do ye wish, O Jews, to crucify me?
Is it because I have strengthened your cripples?
Is it because I raised your dead as from the sleep,
Healed the woman of her issue of blood,
And showed mercy upon the Canaanites woman?
For what act oe juice desire you my death.
But ye shall behold him whom ye pierced, O law transgressors, and know that he is Christ.
So that's that one hymn.
And you know, this is not something that is like it's not new.
There's some people that look at some of these and they're like, whoa, whoa, whoa, but actually
this is just a recapitulation of themes from this.
scriptures, and again indeed from the Old Testament. So yeah, so we're going to give
an example from the Old Testament that is the same kind of thing.
So there are plenty of these as well.
Yeah, there are lots, right, right. There are lots. This is not the exact same words, but
I think you're going to hear the same kind of theme here and with this sort of a similar
kind of rhetoric. So this is from Jeremiah chapter 3 verses 19 through 21.
This is God speaking.
I thought how I would set you among my sons and give you a pleasant land.
This is God speaking to Israel by the way.
A heritage most beautiful of all nations.
And I thought you would call me my father and would not turn from following me.
Surely as a faithless wife leaves her husband so you have been faithless to me.
O house of Israel says Yahweh.
The voice on the bear height is heard, the weeping and pleading of Israel's sons.
because they perverted their way.
They have forgotten the Lord, their God.
So it's again, it's sort of,
as of course, it's typical, especially with Jeremiah,
this kind of lamenting,
God saying, I did this for you, I did this for you,
I did this for you, and yet you turned away.
And yet you sinned against me.
And so it's exact same kind of rhetoric
in both that Holy Week him and then this particular example
from Jeremiah, but again.
again, many such cases, both from Holy Week and from the Old Testament.
And this should help us understand what's going on in these Holy Week texts.
Because unfortunately, we have some folks who don't understand what is going on in these
Holy Week texts.
Yeah, there are people who look at the Holy Week texts and see these things, these critical
things addressed to Israel and words.
the Jews or the Jews, yeah, or really like Judeans is kind of a better, better translation
although the way it reads in English is usually the Jews.
The Jews, right.
And they say, well, that's anti-Semitism, that's blemeshifting, that's whatever, right?
And what I'll say to that is, and we'll get much deeper into why that's so super wrong.
but there's a-
very elementary way to know why that's wrong without getting into the deeper reason, which
is way more interesting, by the way. But the elementary reason is that it should be very
clear the historical context of the events of the gospels is first century Palestine.
There's nothing in those hymns and there's nothing in the Old Testament texts, but there's
So, secretly, there's nothing in those hymns when it's talking about Jesus' passion and
death.
and so forth. That is assigning this to some racial group, right? It's addressed to the people
who were there and did those things at the time. And as a way we have pointed out in the
atonement episode, as I recall, and when this has been talked about, you know, blood being on people,
If you look at the Torah, when blood goes upon people.
it's to cleanse them. So that language that's in the scriptures that sometimes people say,
well that's anti-Semitic, you know his blood be upon us and on our children is actually a prophecy
about Christ's atonement, about Christ's cleansing of the world. So it's actually a blessing. Now,
is it the case that some people in history have looked at these kinds of texts, whether
their hymns or...
stuff in the scriptures and so forth and have turned it into actual racist anti-semitism,
hate all Jews everywhere, every when. Yes, they have. That is wrong. That is a misreading
of the scriptures. That is a misreading of these hymns. So on its face, it's a misreading.
But let's look underneath the face a little bit and see the deeper reason why this is a
a very wrong way to read this stuff.
And...
And to clarify that too, remember ideas don't cause things, right?
Indeed, no.
People who have hated the Jewish people for a variety of reasons,
social, cultural, economic, all kinds of reasons,
have weaponized these texts against them.
Yeah, right.
Right.
Um, yeah.
But so the core of the issue here is, the core of the issue here is,
And this is in line with a lot of critiques we've made.
of liberal theological movements is that you have people of a certain liberal
sensibility and they realize that part of understanding what the
scriptures say, the Christian scriptures say, and early Christian
hemnography and the Church Fathers and and and.
Part of what that means when we say that Jesus is the Jewish Messiah, because by the way,
nobody else had a Messiah, right?
The Norwegians, the Romans, the Chinese people were not waiting for a Messiah, right?
So when we say Jesus is the Jewish Messiah, that kind of entails that that means
Jewish person who doesn't accept Jesus as the Messiah is rejecting their Messiah. Right.
And if we accept that Jesus is the God of Israel, that a Jewish person who rejects that is
to some extent rejecting who their God is.
And if we accept that the Hebrew Scriptures are teaching about Jesus as the Messiah, then
we are saying to Jewish people that they don't understand their Bible, they don't understand
their Scriptures correctly.
And people of a certain liberal sensibility don't want to say those things, the second part,
right?
Of all those statements.
Great.
It offends their sensibilities, right, to say that about Jewish people.
And because the worst thing that can happen to them is for them to appear bad in public,
or to face some kind of accusation like that they were anti-Semitic or something, they
decide to go the whole route and just be
come anti-Semitic. What do I mean by that? In order to not say that Jewish people have rejected
their Messiah by not accepting Jesus, they try to get rid of the idea that Jesus is the Jewish Messiah.
And this warps and skews their theology until Jesus just becomes the savior of the world.
Yeah, which he is, but, but his Jewishness gets ripped away.
way. Yeah. Right? And we don't want to say that Jewish people have misunderstood their
God who they worship. So he's no longer the God of Israel. All the Jewishness gets stripped
away. Now he's just Plato's God or God in general, the God of the whole universe, the God
who created everything, just God, God. Yeah, which that is the basis for why people reject
the kind of language that we've just been reading.
But if you regard God as sort of the generic God, the platonic God that's out there somewhere,
contemplating himself, then the idea that you would inject is specificity of the relationship
of God with his people, Israel, that's necessitated then.
You have to reject that specificity because that does that seem weird that he's the God
probably these people, you know, but that is what the scripture says is that he's
the God of Israel, and for him to then be, I mean, there is a sense in which, of course,
he is the God of every single person and place and thing in the universe.
That is true.
But he has also revealed himself as the God of Israel.
And that means that his relationship to Israel is different than his relationship to everything
else, which means then if you want that relationship, you have to become part of Israel, right?
Which is what the church is.
I'm sure that-
future episode will go into some great detail about that relationship. But yeah, you can't
escape the Israel stuff. You can't escape the Jewish stuff and be an actual Christian.
Right. And they don't want to say Jewish people have misunderstood the Hebrew Scriptures
they're Bible. And so they we just we're just going to ignore the Old Testament.
Yeah, which again, that is the core of that's the core of Israel.
You know
to be Jewish is that those scriptures. So as Christians, we just won't read that or talk about it
at all and we'll warp our reading of the New Testament so that it doesn't require the Old Testament.
Right. And we'll take it in this other direction where it's disconnected. Sorry, crypto-marshi
units. Yeah. Right. So, and so this is the most anti-Semitic thing possible.
Because what you end up with is a white liberal and lightened religious class.
that has this universal religion with a universal God and a universal Savior,
right? And then, oh, well, yeah, we let the Jews go and do their thing in the corner
over there. And we let them be and we respect their traditions, right? Which is
infantilizing to them, right? That's anti-Semitism, folks.
The people who want to edit your Holy Week book and take out all the references to the
Jews, the people who want to make Christianity not Jewish anymore, they're the anti-Semites.
Okay?
They're the ones with the colonial attitude.
That's where they've ended up.
So, don't get confused about that.
Right. In their concern for their public reputation, right, and not wanting to be accused of anything or look anti-semitic, they go mask off with their actual anti-semitism.
Okay. So that rant done kind of, I'm going to revisit that in my final comments. So get ready.
But what we've been talking about in this third half is
how Jesus embodies the God of Israel.
It was a very particular God, right?
The living God, the actual God.
But we've done that again.
We're not saying this is all that's to be said about that.
We're not saying any of those things.
But this is a way of approaching that from the bottom up
in terms of the people who encountered Jesus
and first encountered him as as far as they could initially tell a human
how they came to understand that he
embodied Israel's God and how that was part of what led them to identify him as
the Messiah.
Amen.
Well, just to give my own final thoughts, I'm not going to be throwing out any anti-semitism
mic drops. I will leave that to you my friend. Although I enjoyed it a lot.
You know, this episode for me has been very illuminating because one of the core questions
in the Gospels that Jesus asks people is, is who do you say that I am?
And it's not like a quiz when he says that to them.
Like, let me see how much Christology you guys got down.
So who do you say that I am?
And of course the responses you are the Christ, the s**t.
son of the living God. You are the Messiah. They recognized that he was the Messiah. And we just
spent the last couple hours going over exactly what that means. When Peter said that, when anyone else
said that, I should mention by the way that it was Saint Andrew who first introduced Saint Peter
to Jesus instead of Messiah. I just got to get that in there.
But so how does that apply for us? Right? It's it's it's it's useful and valuable for us to ask
we what did people in the first century in first century policy and how did they understand this man
that they met? Why did they say that he was the Messiah? Right? How does that apply for us?
Because it might come across as some sort of well this is a very interesting intellectual exercise
you know casting our minds back 2000 years and seeing what they might have saw seen and try to
Imagine first.
but now we live in this point where all or most of the prophecies have been fulfilled and so on and so forth.
So how does that apply? Right?
So here's the thing.
For someone to be a Christian means that they have met Christ.
It means that they had the experience that St. John talks about at the end of his gospel,
says, these are written that you may believe that Jesus is the Christ and that
believing you may have life in His name. And of course, as we've said, I don't
know how many thousand times in this podcast, believing there is not just about
agreeing. It's about becoming faithful. So these are written that you may be
faithful to Jesus the Christ. And that being faithful, you may have life in
this name.
That is another way to read that exact same verse.
So what does it mean for us to have that meeting with Christ to become faithful
to that revelation of Him as the Messiah?
Well
It means a lot of different things for different people and by that I don't mean well, you know
Whatever it means to you
I don't mean that. I'm not throwing out some kind of theological
But I am saying that people encounter the Lord Jesus Christ in different ways. He reveals
himself to people in different ways. Some people they enter into the beauty and the worship
of the church, and they meet God. It's hardly any other way to describe it. They meet him.
the middle of Jesus.
Some people, they study the scriptures very closely and over time,
the realization comes upon them and Christ reveals them, himself to them, through their experience
of the scriptures. Some people receive unconditional love from someone and let's face it,
that is a rarer commodity in this world than it should be even from family.
and in that unconditional love, Christ reveals Himself to them.
And for many people at some combination of those things are something else.
But it's coming upon that truth, and by that I don't just mean a mental understanding,
but the truth, knowing, knowing that He is the Christ, that He is the Messiah,
that he is the one
that we have hoped for. That's how the apostles put it. That's how the apostles put it.
And that's the basis for our being Christian is that we encountered Christ. We found him and this
is where we're going to follow him is here in the church because this is his body. This is where
where he is. This is where he's revealing himself. This is where when we say Christ is in our
Let's get started.
It really is true. Christ isn't our midst.
And so when we talk about who Jesus is, right, it's not about Christology as some kind of precise theological academic discipline,
although it's important to have that precise theological language.
But as Father Stephen said earlier, the point of that dogmatic language is to create boundaries past which we don't wander off.
This, the dogmatic language does not encapsulate who the Lord Jesus is.
Right? It just puts those boundaries around the edge.
There is an encounter with the risen Christ, an encounter with Jesus of Nazareth, the Messiah of Israel,
that each of us has and can have and sometimes begins at one point and unfolds over a lifetime.
There's a whole narrative dynamic to it for each one of us.
And I'm not talking about some kind of like woo-woo spiritual experience, although some people
have experiences that probably could be described in that way.
That's not what I mean.
I'm talking about the revelation of Christ to you.
And, you know, I've, father, I've heard you stay in the past that.
someone comes to your parish. I mean, I agree with this. Someone comes to your parish and they want to become orthodox.
For any reason other than here I meet Christ, here I see Christ, here I wish to follow Christ,
that it's not time for them yet.
Because this is what Christianity is.
It's the way of life
in which we encounter the Lord Jesus.
and we follow him and we become more like him and we are incorporated into him. That's what Christianity is.
All the other things that sort of fan out from that can be very important and helpful and so on,
so forth. But there is a center and this is what it is. This is why the gospel is preached.
This is why the gospel is that Jesus is the Messiah.
That is why that is...
central part of that proclamation. This is who he is. This is what he did. This is what he expects from us.
And so my hope for this episode is that it will have contributed to those of you who are listening to
this. It will have contributed to your vision of Jesus as the Messiah. That's the one sent by God,
the anointed one sent by God to be...
The Savior of Israel and the Savior in as much as we are incorporated into Israel of the
world and the one who has reclaimed his throne in the heavens and whose kingdom shall
have no end.
So that's what I have to say about that.
So one of the...
things we've lost in the contemporary world is a sense of heritage. And that's for a whole pile of reasons.
Right. You know, late capitalism turning us all into consumers, units of consumption before that it was units of labor.
intense individualism. We see our own life as a story and an end in in and of
itself.
We don't see ourselves having any real direct connection to our ancestors beyond the curiosity
of going and figuring out our family tree and learning about them maybe.
But we certainly don't see them as sort of living on in us or we don't interpret our
personal experience and our personal identity in terms of their experience anymore.
And what do I mean by that? Well, if you read, as of course I do, being a priest every
time I celebrate the liturgy, if you read the prayers in the ennapper of the divine liturgy,
whether we're talking about St. Basil the Great, St. John Chrysostom, what you find is you
get a sense of the identity of the people of the community that is spraying these prayers.
And the heritage, it's expressed as an experience of the people there praying them.
Sort of parallel to in the way in Passover.
The way Passover was celebrated was we celebrated was
that it was not the family saying this is the day on which our ancestors were brought out of Egypt.
Right? This isn't like when we are brought out of Egypt. We were slaves in Egypt.
us sitting around this table. What you find in the divine liturgy, because our
divine liturgy prayers come from communities that were not primarily,
honestly not even significantly Jewish by that point, is you find a
reflection of the actual experience of us Gentiles which is that God called us
away.
and set us free from the worship of idols.
That God brought us from idolatry, sexual immorality,
violence, all of those things
to worship the true and living God, the God of Israel, the God of
Abraham, Isaac and Jacob.
And it's expressed in the prayers is that happening to us who
are gathered there, not my distant ancestors, us.
And that's a sense of identity and heritage that I don't think is real for a lot of us
as Christians anymore.
I like a lot of people bulk at it.
One of the harshest responses I get from people is when I point out that someone Greek hears
it that, sorry, Greek folks, I love you, but your ancestors were demon worshipping
petrass.
That's what they were.
Forget about the-
democracy stuff.
It's the same truth for almost all of us.
Right.
Pretty much.
I'm getting there.
Forget the democracy stuff, forget the other stuff.
Right.
That was the reality.
And then a Jewish guy named Saul of Tarsus showed up.
Showed up in Athens.
He showed up in Corinth.
He showed up in Thessaloniki.
And he spoke to your ancestors and he told your ancestors,
about the true and living God, and he told your ancestors about the Jewish Messiah.
And he explained the Hebrew Scriptures translated into Greek for their sake to your ancestors,
so that they could leave that and be set free from that to worship the true and living God.
As Jesus says in St. John's Gospel, salvation is from the Jews.
Right and as I just said to Father Andrew
I'm getting to it, right? Well, that was happening in the Greeks. We're starting to become Christians.
My ancestors were still painting themselves blue and dancing around fires and killing and eating
their neighboring tribesmen. Okay. So not saying minds were better, right? But eventually,
eventually the gospel got up there too, right, to the lowlands. Eventually it got there. I'm also
part Greek by the way, it's a small part but...
it. That's what happened. That's part of who I am and who you are as a Gentile Christian.
That's part of our story. Our story is a story of getting grafted in, as St. Paul says,
to the tree that has Abraham as its root, so that Abraham is the father of many nations.
So that Jewish heritage.
becomes part spiritually of my heritage.
But there's this danger.
There's danger that comes, as we were saying in my previous rant, right,
of people who want to departicularize the gospel.
Who want to remove the Jewishness of Christianity? Christianity is Judaism.
It is a form of Judaism. Not it was, it is. Right? Our argument with rabbinic Judaism is,
who's right about Judaism? Right? It's not about, it's not two different religions. Right?
It's, it's who has Judaism right? Who has the Torah right? Who has the Messiah right? That's,
the disagreement.
And to try to de-judgeize the Scriptures to de-judgeize Christianity, try and remember
that we'll always distort what Christianity is.
We'll always warp what Christianity is.
to concern that...
People currently have about not wanting to look anti-Semitic
Or being queasy
Right about disagreeing with Jewish people about their own scriptures
Needs to be redirected
Needs to be redirected the way St. Paul directed it
Rather than being concerned about how we look
We should be concerned about the
salvation of Jewish people. We should long for a day and pray that a day comes. When the
Patriarchate of Jerusalem gets overtaken by waves of Jewish people embracing Jesus as
the Messiah and becoming Christians, that should be a day that we hope and pray will come.
But what that requires is actual love for Jewish people.
Not wanting to justify myself and not appear anti-Semitic or hateful or judgmental.
Not having a condescending attitude toward Jewish people will let them have their religion.
That requires me to actually love them.
want them to fully embrace the truth.
of their Messiah, their God, their heritage, their covenants.
That's the attitude we see reflected in Christ, in St. Paul, in the Scriptures, in the church, in our liturgics.
and that's the attitude we need to...
shift back to having. And the way back to that I think comes from
re-embracing the truth of our heritage. That I was once an idolator,
I was once lost in immorality, I was once lost in violence and bloodshed.
And then the word came to me about the Jewish Messiah,
Messiah and that person I was died and a new person came into a...
existence. And that new person has Abraham as a father. So those are my final. Amen. Amen.
That is our show for tonight everyone. Thank you very much for listening. If we didn't actually
get to talk to you live tonight, which we didn't actually get any calls tonight
about any of this. But we'd like to hear from you. You can email us at Lordofspiritsneed.frate.com.
You can make...
messages on our Facebook page where you can leave us a voice.
But let's speak pipe.com slash Lord of the Spirits.
And if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or need help finding
a parish, head over to orthodoxintro.org.
And join us for our live broadcast of the second and fourth Thursdays of the
month at 7 PM Eastern 4 PM Pacific.
You've got your arms held out like you've been carrying a load.
And you swear to me you don't want to be my slave.
If you're undaring at me like I need to be saved.
You're on Facebook, follow our page join our discussion group, leave a comment.
reviews and ratings everywhere, but most importantly, share the show with one of your friends
who is going to benefit from it.
And finally, be sure to go to www.anxierfate.com.stokesupport and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
I swear to you, I would never feed you pain, but you're staring at me.
Like I need you.
Thank you, good night.
God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts and the elders,
and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom
and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Chapter 5, verses 11-12.